hello everyone it's December 13 2022
we're in active bookstream number 1.02
on the book governing continuous
transformation off to Blue
hi everyone
we are the
participatory online learning Institute
that is learning practicing and thinking
about applied active inference you can
reach us here at all of our media links
this is a recorded and an archives live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve upon our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we will be following
good video etiquette for live streams
hopefully
um get in touch if you want to
participate either in this uh bookstream
or the dot zero contextualization
contextualization streams or in another
live stream or maybe in the discussion
stream
um you can reach us always at active.org
or by email
okay so here we are bookstream 1.02 the
sections will go through the book map
and the roadmap the keywords and the
claims and we'll be continuing the
discussion of governing continuous
transformation
so I don't know if we want to just maybe
mention a couple of things one or two
things that we're excited to discuss
more today or learn more about from this
section of the book Tyler is there
anything that stood out for you
specifically or maybe you want to give
an introduction and then
um maybe say one or two words about the
book The chapter yeah sure so uh I'm
Tyler I work more on the applied side of
thinking about governance organizational
design uh both work in like the Dow
tooling space and also protocol design
also working a lot of like corporate
settings or as a strategy consultant
um I think for today what I'm excited
about is that you know I went to
business school something that I you
know hear a lot about like some of these
you know organizational design
Frameworks that Bijan references in the
book that's really interesting to
compare that directly to free energy
governance and compare contrast to see
where the gaps are so I'm excited about
exploring that more today
uh I am really excited to
um kind of Link uh and so I'll do this
right up in the very beginning but but
to link what we have talked about in the
active Insurance Institute over the last
couple of years about biological
organization
um and hierarchical like information
flow in biological systems I'm excited
to connect that to how that works in an
organization so so I just as I was
reading the book that was something that
stood out to me as something that's
maybe necessary for
um like a more elaborate discussion of
the text
uh cool Daniel anything
Oliver
comment at the road map but I'm Daniel
I'm a researcher in California and just
looking forward to this discussion
cool thanks okay
uh so here we are at the book map we are
in chapter two sensing sense making and
strategic renewal
and the roadmap for today is just two
sections these were structured actually
by the author strategic cognition
sensing and sense making and the second
section is strategic renewal
did you want to make a comment here
Daniel
at the roadmap
um
not yet thank you
okay
um okay so lots of keywords in today's
uh discussion so we'll just jump right
in and hopefully we put them in an order
that aligns with the order in the book
and um included some commentary and
claims from the text as well
all right so Tyler do you want to read
this first part of the abstract
sure
um a sentence sense making form one
uteri acts and together considered a
non-operational cognitive meta
capability or dynamic capability there's
no sensing without sense making and vice
versa and there is no organizational
sense making in the absence of a clearly
defined deep existential corporate
purpose generally the processes of top
down bottom-ups hypothesizing prediction
error immunization rather than top-down
risks application or guiding the path
navigating a discontinuous world there's
neurosciences predictive coding that
allows us to take management researches
strategic cognition and more
specifically connected structure and
cognition and one step further to
provide a more complete and practice
relevant framework for applying sensing
and sense making in the context of
strategic renewal
boom I'm gonna take the next part sure
thanks Daniel do you want to read this
part no
I'll do it
uh effectively sensing and sense making
are empowered by the circular causality
of top-down knowledge structures
prediction models predictions hypotheses
and guesses and bottom up stimuli data
stemming from resource markets by
default uncertainty and complexity are
subjective Concepts but are consistently
deployed in management research as
subjectively determined environmental
sensing and sense making are nonsensical
in the absence of having set the firm's
purpose and context in the first place
once we Define sensing sense making and
strategic renewal in form of
action-centric circular causality
linking purpose prediction models
predictions and prediction error
minimization a new logic of strategic
renewal emerges dynamically connecting
structure hierarchy cognition and
capabilities
um and so that I I just really wanted to
bring this in um here we were talking
here about top down and bottom up and I
know that that's like there's management
styles and structures that are
associated with top down and bottom-up
like management styles
um but I really wanted to bring up this
paper the information theory of
individuality by David krakauer and
colleagues at the Santa Fe Institute and
I bring this up because really they try
to Define what is an individual so so
even in a biological system an
individual like we are we have more or
just as many cells inside of our body
that are not human as we do cells that
are human right but like if you were to
take all of those non-human cells out of
my body like I would not be the same
person like I would not function
optimally at all so I'm more maybe than
just what is my DNA like there's a I'm a
colony right not not necessarily like
I'm one organism I'm many organisms to
function appropriately and so really
these guys tried to Define fine not how
you like contain an individual like what
is worthy of this Markov blanket like we
talk about the Markov blanket as the
boundary between internal and external
but like where do you put that am I
drawing it around like my human cells
between my human cells and my non-human
cells like that doesn't really make
sense right and so they talk in this
paper a lot about um and they do it in a
hierarchical way which is why this the
biological levels of organization are
here because you can define an
individual like at the level of a cell
or a tissue or an organ organism
population community and so forth and
this even applies to organizations like
a company uh so so here the what is
critical it for to be defined as an
individual is this bi-directional
information flow and and I I think that
this paper is very elegant and great so
you have to have information flowing top
down and you also have to have
information flowing bottom up to be like
worthy of a Markov blanket and um
considered an individual in this paper
and so I really just kind of wanted to
bring that in because they talk about it
Bijan talks a lot about how you need
this bottom up and top down and they
have to work together and he talks about
that a lot in the in the book for a firm
to persist and so like really it's
necessary for anything to persist like
you have to have that bi-directional
information flow to earn your Markov
blanket so to speak uh so I just wanted
to kind of bring that up here before we
jump in to um the additional context
talking about top down and bottom up um
in the book did you guys have any
comments here
Daniel yeah but I was going to uh
suggest that the road map was a quote
from the abstract subjective Concepts
pragmatically applied which I think
deals with a lot of informational
Concepts and then like you brought up if
you Define self
uh spatially or genetically you're going
to get some boundaries which may be
relevant in certain situations but also
might give a misleading or partial view
of the total system
and then the challenges when we move to
this informational or statistical theory
of nested selves then organizations and
their niches can have many different
looking causes and components so it's
very
challenging and it's not the org chart
it's not the computer access chart it's
something that's somehow different and I
think that'll be relevant to pull out
what is being described and what should
people's consideration be
what do we actually gain by saying that
systems are nested which isn't a novel
insight
yeah that's great and and then like also
you know in talking about that like you
know bi-directional information flow
like the there's a certain amount of
salience that has to be there also like
information can be flowing both
directions but if the information is
irrelevant then then that's going to you
know not not be the cause for
perseverance right
um
okay cool
okay so here we are uh strategic
cognition sensing and sense making and
just um a early quote from this chapter
do you want to read this Tyler is that
okay
um all right strategy initiation and
formulation defined as a complex complex
activity consisting of scanning sense
making and strategic decision making are
at the heart of the firm's Collective
intuitive power emphasizing as core
capabilities timely and accurate reading
of expected environmental change in the
corresponding need for resource
reconfiguration and pursuit of the debt
adaptation
cool thank you
um okay so strategic cognition uh they
used the definition
um presented in this paper the cognitive
perspective in strategy and integrated
review and they referenced this paper
quite a bit so I just pulled out this
diagram of strategic cognition and
pulled up the definition that was used
in this paper so they say strategic
cognition is discussed in terms of its
consent constituents structure and
process by structure we refer to the
relatively stable characteristics and
repeated patterns of behavior and by
process to the cognitive activities
taking place in organizations
just a note on that the focus in this
book
is on kind of a certain type of
Corporation with a board of directors
for example which is an important
category
this I'm also just imagining uh someone
who is navigating spatially as part of
like working in a taxi service also
strategic cognition is coming into play
though the wording might be framed a
little differently but it's similar
questions about sense making and just
different implementations of different
kinds of organizations
and I wonder how um like strategy in
terms of this kind of strategic
cognition is related to like the systems
engineering approach is it like aligned
with that or maybe not
um that's something be interesting to to
know more about
do you have any comments here Tyler
yeah I think that's actually something
that uh to build on Daniel's Point like
how specific would be John is talking
about is to board specifically versus
other organizational structures and just
like a comment on that my initial
feelings on so far where we are in the
book is that it's really not I'm not
seeing why we need to reduce the scope
of just like organizations that have
boards especially since like most
companies I've been in a lot of the
important decision making is really
happening at the level of
um really more of the executives in the
c-suite and the Zhang might argue like
hey that's actually a problem it should
be more coming from an active board
um but it's kind of interesting to see
like where are the limits of what the
genre is talking about and how specific
is it to a specific kind of
organizational structure
or another angle is in the body the
decisions are being made in a
distributed nested way and so that kind
of organization I think will read on to
find will have resonance with this
however who should the Strategic
communication and Cutting Edge research
on the strategy governance Upstream
decision making there's a very certain
audience I think it makes sense to
communicate that too and also this is
the
threads being linked for a first time in
a dissertation style book
and I could imagine different kinds of
presentations and implementations being
presented differently not necessarily
like an academic published dissertation
and that leads me to wonder perhaps
strategic cognition can take place at
many levels in a hierarchical system
like maybe you know an individual like a
project or a team is doing strategic
cognition on the execution of their
goals and tasks and that happens you
know at the level of the individual and
the team and the project and the you
know department and then the firm and
then the board so perhaps it occurs um
in several places so like when I've been
reading board when Johnson's board I
read that as like counsel and that's my
like interpretation of that and that can
happen at many levels as well
funny like when you say counsel I think
attorney like why do we have lawyers
involved I mean council is in like high
Council Supreme Council
all right awesome okay uh so sensing
um I I pulled this out to Tyler's uh you
know protests
um I wanted to just maybe talk a little
bit about sensing and sense making
um and talk a little bit about them
separately but but they are sensing and
sensing sensing and sensing and sense
making form one unitary act and together
can be considered a non-operational
cognitive meta capability or dynamic
capability and this uh reminds me of the
time that I asked Carl about like when
I'm sensing what am I sensing like if I
am I sensing like when I look at a red
balloon am I sensing red balloon or am I
sensing like
700 nanometer wavelength of light and
like round oval shape like what is
actually being perceived via the senses
and so like there is actually and Carla
answered me he said red balloon like go
away from the red light and go more
towards the Red Balloon and so like that
that answer really says like okay there
actually is not sensing without sense
making like they are inextricably linked
because if I'm actually sensing red
balloon like then I'm actually like I'm
going beyond what like my eyes see or
like what my nose smells or whatever
um okay and effectively sensing and
sense making is a form of organizational
learning action-centric hypothesis
testing that connects the individual
level with that of the firm
um do you guys have any comments here we
can move on to sense making
or stay in sense making Maybe
uh all right Tyler this is yours
all right sense making so purpose goal
directedness so the world's fundamental
the world's models underlying prediction
model is fundamental to sense sing and
sense making so dissonance is a function
that a preset goal generating
predictions and submitting those
predictions to can you continue
continuous error minimization since
making models are constantly adjusted
through error and deviation querying
feedback loops doubling top-down
predictions and bottom-up stimuli and
circular causality the sole objective
and minimizing prediction errors and
surprise ID free energy fundamentally
since making is about designing noticing
systems
um and so a quote that I really liked
from the paper that um is actually from
uh wake I'm not sure if I'm pronouncing
that right is sense making is about how
people deal with situations where there
are too many or too few meanings
um and this is something that I've
experienced a lot especially in like
startup contexts like you could think of
it and they're actually kind of the same
situation too many or too few meanings
like if you're in a startup and you're
trying to figure out what you do next
like your strategic directions are like
kind of infinite because you haven't
really built that many so like there's
like all these things directions you can
go things you're hearing and the
ecosystem like oh if we did this look we
did this and like that all could be
meaningful but at the same time it all
collapses into like what are we actually
doing like are we even building anything
right now like what's the point of any
of this
um and so I love how that kind of shows
up in your like in the for example in a
health context I was show up in the body
as kind of like illness or the stealing
of agitation anxiety and you kind of
have that same embodied feeling both in
yourself and in the organization of like
hey like what we're doing isn't working
we're having all of these like
communication
um kind of issues where like the
breakdowns where I'm not you're not
receiving what I'm telling you the the
information I'm telling you about
problem isn't being received correctly
and acted upon and it just like boils up
into becoming a bigger issue until where
something needs to to happen and some
action needs to be taken and so it's
really like the social process not
something that's like the CEO being like
wow like let me like go in here and like
figure out the root issue like a plumber
would and then like tell you tell the
organization what happened but it's more
of this kind of like feeling of
agitation that happens throughout the
organ uh the organization and through
the social process being like what is
going on what are we doing people
getting increasingly flustered uh
something is birthed in that process and
something that actually had like a
personal realization when I was reading
uh this chapter because I used to work
as a strategy consultant and strategy
consultant what I kind of realized about
that job is that it's purely about sense
making so a lot of times people think of
strategy Consultants as like oh you're
doing like a complicated quantitative
analysis you give that to the board of
directors they make a decision super top
down but actually where we spent most of
our time on was socialization like kind
of talking to people like kind of
knowing when we went into the
organization like roughly what was going
on in a certain way we collect data I
kept talking to people but even when we
were like we're pretty sure we had the
answer
most of the job was actually Framing and
communication and like talking to a
bunch of people and using the language
that they use and making sure that
there's a shared narrative between
everyone and so like that was where the
real work is I was like oh that's
interesting like management Consultants
are professional sense makers and I
think a lot of times a lot of
organizations are actually embedding
management Consultants within the
organization as a way of like sense
making as like a capability that an
organization uh would have and so like
an example of something I had as a
Management Consultant where you kind of
feel this dissonance was like I worked
for a lot of like health insurance
companies and so health insurance
companies were having this problem where
well at least in the U.S skyrocketing
healthcare costs and if you're a health
insurance company you're basically a
payment processor and so you don't
really have any levers to fix that and
so there's this issue of like okay well
we we need to bring in costs but like we
don't have any levers to do that uh and
so what that means is that you have to
become more of a like a care manager to
some extent and like that is a totally
different way of like contextualizing
like who you are both on the
organization level and on the individual
level of like what is like my purpose
here in this role in this organization
was this organization trying to do and
getting to the Care Management side like
totally needs to shift that and so that
shows up in the organization has a lot
of dissonance a lot of angst uh and also
like a lot of pain
um and it ends up meaning that both the
organization needs to change but also
this individual needs to change
themselves and how they relate to that
organization and so that's why I like
this cartoon of like I've been
restructured as like a lot of times it's
like you are have to re-contextualize
yourself while so the organization is
recontextualizing like what it's trying
to do
um
so yeah I'll leave it there uh Daniel
and blues you have anything to add on
the slide
well that's very insightful and it
reminds me of the two ways that the
entities can reduce free energy by
changing their mind and changing the
world through action and this is an
approach where we can describe that
process happening at multiple nested and
interacted levels
and um even if the niche changed round
one
the world would be different the regime
of attention would be different the
action perception Loop would be
different and that would at the very
least induce anxiety and uncertainty
cognitively so it's really interesting
what you added
and I just love your cartoon the face
pulled out it's good
okay
so here is a claim from the book from
the chapter on a more operational level
sense making is very Effectiveness is
shaped by three critical Dimensions
first the clarity of a Timeless
corporate purpose second a
dissonance-centric quest for and
optimization of filtering anomalies as
anomalies become shared sensibleness
should become stronger
and c and an activist worldview I.E
environment is not exogenously
predetermined but is enacted through the
social and action-centric construction
of shared meaning
um and so like let's talk about
dissonance a little bit
um
going back to this quote unless you guys
have comments here
no Okay so
fundamentally firm level sensing and
sense making grounded in dissonance
theory are a social process rather than
a singular activity dedicated to
detecting anomalies and I think that
this goes back to what Tyler was
actually just talking about but I looked
up like the theory and this is the the
citation that Bijan used and in this
text
um festinger says in short I'm proposing
the dissonance that is the existence of
non-fitting relations among cognitions
is a motivating factor in its own right
by the term cognition here and in the
remainder of the book I mean any
knowledge opinion or belief about the
environment oneself or one's Behavior
cognitive dissonance can be seen as an
antecedent condition which leads to
activity activity oriented toward
dissonance reduction just as hunger
leads to activity oriented toward hunger
reduction it is a very different
motivation from what psychologists are
used to dealing with but as we shall see
nonetheless powerful
um and so when we talk about sensing and
sense making being grounded in
dissonance theory this is something
Tyler and I uh had discussed
um offline back channel uh we were we
were talking about dissonance theory and
and what we're interpreting this to mean
here is that um it is this like disjoint
activity like the like the like a
mismatch between maybe like individual
and firm level cognition or firm level
cognition and like societal expectations
or anyway like there's a a gap
um it that causes like a kind of
discomfort that needs to then be filled
um but I would be excited to hear maybe
Bijan talk more about how it's grounded
in dissonance theory like
um
just because it's it's it was kind of
unclear from the text like what exactly
that might mean
um but if you guys have any comments
here Daniel
yeah
um in active inference we might think
about dissonance as being related to a
Divergence like a KL Divergence and so
dissonance isn't a state of exception
and kind of a binary switch there's
always some non-zero level of Divergence
between expectations and incoming
sensory data if only because the
generative model is coarse grained so in
the decimal points the world always is
going to be somewhat surprising or at
least evaluatable in terms of surprise
so again instead of centering for
example absolute value attainment and
then seeing uncertainty as a secondary
characteristic we use divergence-based
statistics to incorporate this idea of
dissonance or Divergence driven behavior
and put that at the center of the
imperative for action
yeah I I interpreted uh the jeans could
bring a dissonance theory as like way of
bridging about the individual cognition
so like the social cognition and like
had a feeling of anxiety manifest in an
organization uh and so like I think
Disney's Theory at least in this quote
might be referring to the individual
specifically
um and have that individual But anxiety
of like hey I thought I was going to
give the promotion this year I didn't
get a promotion this year something is
wrong or like hey we I worked really
hard on this feature it didn't increase
conversions in the way I thought it
would that feels bad that's not
motivating for me right that's like on
the individual level but then you can
there's another way you can interpret
that dissonance on a more of like a
social level as a way in like more of a
social cognition
cool all right
non-uniformity Tyler
all right
um
all right it's critical that the
environment throughput listening to what
wants to emerge is neither logic nor
goal trapped but open to non-informity
in fact the throughput of non-informing
is a measure firms survivability and
certainty and surprise are not to be
avoided but to be minimized through
action hypothesis testing Centric
engagement with the world as the
underlying World model consequently and
generally gains an informational Edge
and so we talked about this a little bit
uh during the last bookstream but a lot
of looters want to imagine that they're
like slowly ironing out non-uniformity
uh and that like you're you're creating
this perfect perfect organizational
design and it's actually kind of funny
like there's this trap that a lot of
leaders get into and I've actually gone
into this myself where like it's kind of
like a Utopia design almost actually
it's exactly the same thing as utopia
decide where you're like I'm gonna have
this model of like where I'm gonna like
all these problems I perceive in the
world like I'm just gonna fix by just
like top down just like God mode
figuring it out and then like everything
is going to be there and like we're not
gonna have to worry about anything
anymore it's gonna be great
um and then like invariably like your
two weeks you create a new org design
two weeks and it works for like a week
and people are excited about it and then
like you start seeing kind of ruffles at
the edge you start like trying to patch
things up and then it like all
disintegrates
um and then like I think a lot of
leaders are like oh well like you know
people we have the wrong people people
are you know following process like I
want them to right and it gets really
frustrating
um but I think even when it goes well
it's just like you were missing out on
kind of the like how generative that
non-uniformity can be uh and where
basically like if people are too rigid
in their process you're you're not
carving out space for anything new
um
and so like
the way that Heath Dijon talks about 94
million in this case is that you
minimize it through kind of accident
oriented uh hypothesis testing you're
not like wallowing in this uncertainty
there's a way that you can capture that
and take ownership over uncertainty and
use it for something that's really like
beautiful and productive
um and so like for example you know I've
had jobs where I was a product analyst
and I work for this like consumer
logistics company where we like go into
people's homes and like pack up all of
their things so it's like a very very
complicated job right and so we would
have we would like figure things out
like okay wow our
um times for this kind of job in this
city are going up a lot we would see
that in the data and we're like wow this
is really inefficient and that we would
like that manifest itself as like some
kind of anxiety or dissonance and then
we would like start
um we do analysis and we'd be like oh
it's this kind of job is this kind of
job this kind of furniture then you like
talk to people to talk to some of these
movers and you find out oh they don't
have the right equipment on this uh they
don't have like this kind of wrench on
these particular jobs and like that's
interesting then you socialize that that
information figure out from operations
that that wrench isn't consistently
being returned and they're they're
actually losing a lot of uh their
equipment to be able to do that job then
you find out like uh from other
operational leaders that they're not
being funded appropriately they don't
have like discretional spending to be
able to like actually pay for those
kinds of that kind of equipment right so
it's like through that that anxiety you
kind of like are action oriented and can
figure out like hey like this is not
something that
the situation isn't totally screwed like
we can actually keep moving forward and
like testing figuring out like what's
going on and taking action accordingly
that makes me think of pain and soreness
and redness in the body
like signals have to propagate in order
for things to change and that could be
in an allostatic or an anticipatory or a
reactive or in a traumatized way from
the organism's perspective but the only
way that we're going to find out about
it is through this kind of like active
perception individuals or nested levels
above them making an action-oriented
decision to like sense out different
information and control attention which
is actually seen as a policy selection
over cognitive States
sorry my mouse was sticky
um I am also reminded of biological
systems but maybe for a different reason
so in biology
non-uniformity is critical to existence
like you have a system at equilibrium in
a biological system that's deaf
um like so so this non-uniformity and I
think
um he even brings it up like like as
critical I don't know if I quoted it
here but he brings it up as critical to
um you know survival you have to have
non-uniformity if everything's the same
it's like dull boards like it's it's
just it's it's so um important to have
variety
um variety is the spice of life right
um okay cool all right purpose so
purpose and goal directedness I.E the
world models underlying prediction model
is fundamental to sensing and sense
making and like this is the world
model's underlying model so I just
wanted to point that out that there's
some some nestedness going on here
dissonance is a function of a preset
goal generating predictions and
submitting those predictions to
continuous error minimization
environmental sensing and sense making
are nonsensical in the absence of having
set the firm's existential purpose in
the first place purpose not strategy is
the reason an organization exists its
definition and articulation must be top
Management's first responsibility
um and this reminds me of our like
management
um organization in the active inference
Institute like what is the purpose of
the Institute um and and just trying to
kind of outline and highlight these key
things like like we can't have a
strategy without having a goal to like
like what is that strategy trying to
achieve what is the point right
um if you guys have comments here too
that'd be awesome
it's just that uh
is this meant to be a sentence in one
language or another language even in the
same language or a formal language it
will mean different things to different
people it'll be associated with
different envelopes and portfolios of
risk and positive or negative
consequences also deemed positive and
negative by a different worldview and
contingent upon all these unknown
unknowns so I think amidst that
is where we
can explore a lot of uh
interesting experiences I'm sure and
what has worked and what hasn't worked
in the applied settings and then also
start to synthesize it with the research
on cognitive science and organizational
cognition and that's I think what this
book is about like moving beyond just
recognizing that complexity and starting
to apply active inference and propose
free energy governance as an approach to
step in here and be useful as well as
grounded
yes I don't know like I think I'm
curious if Jean ever gets to point a
book where he really gives some
guidelines for thinking through how to
design purpose more explicitly
um because
journalists has done extremely poorly
even in like major corporations where
they're like our purpose is like
bringing smiles to our consumers or
something like something just like super
big ambiguous that like actually doesn't
really help you at all it's more of
actually like a branding exercise
um and more like a corporate social
responsibility maybe not really anything
about like purpose and when purpose is
done well it's really more like I mean
you guys might disagree with this
this definition but like I think it's
kind of more like a heuristic it's like
a decision rule of like we do this and
not this uh and it's a way of collapsing
information and just being like let's
not think through everything we could be
possibly be doing right now like we
already decided this this is what we're
doing and it's a way to not think about
things uh too
and so I found this to be especially
important in like decentralized context
as well
um and I think this is kind of what free
energy governance is getting towards
like where you have more bottoms up uh
stimuli that you're processing and
changing like these top-down models and
it's really important in that context
because you can't be managing everybody
like really intense things like this is
exactly what you have to do but rather
you have to give a decision rule that a
decentralized group of people can use
independently
um so especially as we get into more
like a free energy governance kind of
world like purpose is super important
but like Daniel touched on like it's not
always totally clear what like a good
purpose even looks like and I hope John
has a very crisp answer later on for
what good purpose is
so like here I am like the non-business
person um and Tyler you said you don't
read like business books but like I've
read more than I like ever wanted to
read
um it just in like my own little startup
uh side Venture
um but but I read a Jim Collins good to
Great Book and he really uh talks about
like purposes really as defining what
you do and what you don't do and and he
really I mean it kind of affronted me I
like he talks about the fox versus the
Hedgehog like you know that the fox
um does lots of things very well he's
very like clever and can can do many
things and the Hedgehog like only has
one thing they do one thing like that's
it they roll up into a ball right like
that's all a hedgehog ever does and so
like in um this fox Hedgehog analogy
like as a company he he says you want to
be a hedgehog and I'm like but but I
want to do so many different things but
but really that having especially like
when I think about a decentralized thing
like we do one thing like I don't know
he talked about like many different
companies but but like you know Wells
Fargo as a bank was a good example like
we are creating the best bank in the
United States of America we're never
banking outside and like maybe it
started regionally and expanded a little
bit or even Southwest we were only going
to fly in the southwest like they just
defined one thing that they were good at
that they could just be better than
everybody else at and just ran with that
and and that is kind of like one of the
defining factors of a great company in
his View
yeah it's actually to build on that a
little bit like it's been a long time
since I arrived good to create but Jim
Collins is kind of like the prototypical
like top-down or what someone calling
orange style of um management whereas
very achievement oriented it's very much
about like the CEO as being the hero
forcing their way and like telling the
organization what to do and focusing
everybody really intensely and so when
you talk about the fox and the Hedgehog
like it's interesting he says you want
to be the Hedgehog because usually when
I hear people sign up with Xbox in the
head challenge like you don't want to be
the Hedgehog like forcing everything
into your narrow World model
um and so I think when he says be the
Hedgehog it's really coming from this
top-down perspective and it's really not
getting into like the free energy
governance model of like we're like
ideally you want to be both the fox and
the Hedgehog we're like you really want
to have
um a unified World model that you're
like hey this world model is like not
true by the way like we all know that
this is subject to change and we're
going to be like actively changing this
but like we all have to be on the same
page and so we're gonna have this kind
of arbitrary belief of what our purpose
is that we're going to continuously
evolve over time uh in a fox-like manner
and so it's like that's a really hard
thing to communicate uh and it's like
very subtle and I've tried to
communicate this in the past often and
effectively
um and so yeah I'm really curious
there's like ways to you know better
combine that fox and Hedgehog you know
model
so like totally now we're spinning out
on a tangent but I just have to say like
I don't know like
I get the whole Fox thing like I I am
very much like aligned mentally with
with how like a fox type of behavior
like because I'm just like oh spiral
like like let me go chase that but but
um the Hedgehog thing like I was
thinking like okay do you really want to
be a fox and a hedgehog or do you want
to be like multiple hedgehogs like I had
this like vision of like dropping water
on the Hedgehog like the little gremlins
you know and you drop the water and then
they multiply and then you have like you
know a little field of hedgehogs that
are all like doing many different things
in a very great way
but all siled and you know they're one
little thing okay we have to we have to
go on Earth we can talk about Gremlins
all day long uh
well so for heuristics I mean this
actually fits into purpose because you
could think of purpose like as a
heuristic and I'm not sure John would
agree with that but that's how I think
about it
um and so read at least a few his
definition was you know cognitive
heuristics are a form of cognitive
simplification or rules of thumb and
tools that empower the human mind what
the poet John keeps called negative
capability the ability to survive and
thrive in an uncertainty
um and so yeah there's just a way of
like collapsing information overload and
finding a way forward despite like not
having the ability to process everything
at the same time
um but then you know Bichon goes on
later to say that heuristics are
fundamentally anchored and we'll deal
with environmental adaptation rather
than enactment so resolving uncertainty
is rather treated as a matter of
adaptation to exogenously determined
game this book rejects environmental
adaptation as a viable survival strategy
and perpetually discontinuous One-Shot
interactions uh environment
um and so
it's just like illustrate this a little
bit because that you know obviously I
think we could all understand like a
heuristic may not be very good you could
use the wrong here in a second how do
you know but just like to make this more
concrete about like how heuristics can
be confusing is that you're like two
like really common heuristics for um
financial planning especially in the
context of startups so one is called
default alive and this was from um uh
Paul Graham he's the font founder of
white combinator and so he says okay a
company should cut costs such that if
you assume constant Revenue growth the
company is going to make a profitability
with the money it has left and so like
that totally makes sense especially in a
startup context where like extreme
uncertainty
but then there's like another decision
rule which is more about expected value
so a company should choose defines a
decision with the highest expected value
expected payoff for the outcome X
um or an outcome times the likelihood of
the outcome and so these aren't like
necessarily incompatible
um well like they can be complementary
to each other but they could tell you to
do very different things uh especially
if like an expected value of like hey we
can crater the business right now is
like a 10 likelihood but we can also or
a 90 likelihood but 10 likelihood we
make you know 100 billion dollar company
right
um and so like that would lead you to do
a different thing than default a live
and so a lot of times Business Leaders
are like juggling both of these at the
same time and not necessarily like
realizing that they are contradictory
heuristics and that there there are
limits to their heuristics
um
so yeah I'll leave it there I've
actually a couple other things that he
says to you are that like you know
simple heuristics can outperform more
complicated ones as well
and it's like actually not even clear on
an organizational level
um how effective heuristics are because
a lot of times when they do studies on
heuristics with individuals where
um everything is
there are not other intelligent actors
who are making anticipations about your
strategy whereas in like a a business
setting there are and so to take like a
very simple example of this like with
design there's for a long time was this
movement of like the heuristic for
design was like oh everything needs to
be super legible and clean
um and like you would use like helvetica
16 point like really like we want this
to be clear and we want information
hierarchy and like that matters far and
above everything else but then the
problem is that everyone was doing that
and it got really monotonous and so the
actual optimal strategy in that case was
to design something totally wacky and
insane and so over the last three years
there was like this especially with the
web three just like absurd like look
like they were like gocds pages from the
90s where it was like looked awful and
it was like not accessible and it was
gross but it was really interesting to
look at
um and they were using fonts that are
totally unreadable but it was
interesting and it was this competitive
situation where like the obvious
heuristic but in a competitive situation
made the optimal strategy doing the
opposite of that heuristic
oh just a few notes there's so many
great points one is the game theory
alpharol bar problem where there's a bar
and you want to go if it's under half
full but not over half full it's not fun
you can't get a drink and it turns out
that that's like an unwinnable game
because if you go well if it was busy
yesterday or if it was busy three nights
ago all decision rules if you just hold
to them get adapted around and I think
then
that's a very interesting light to
reject environmental adaptation
as a strategy position of the book
because I think adapting to the
environment sounds like something
biological it sounds like something that
would be successful organizationally
and then I think that will also lead us
to some discussions of how does the free
energy minimization imperative transcend
the default alive expected value
dialectic
cool
um
all right Buca so this is an acronym for
volatility uncertainty complexity uh and
ambiguity so after some background noise
right now by the way
um so
the I'm just read a quote This is
actually a full disclosure from my aunt
who's a leadership and organizational
design consultant
um she wrote this post called
interpreting explorers in Booga
territory and I really liked how she
framed this where you know most of us in
the west were trained in the
professional model that prize expertise
today being an expert and a specialist
is not enough and worse it can make you
part of the problem because today we're
dealing with the frontiers of humanity a
place where no one has been and no one
could possibly be a Content expert and
so what I really really like about this
is that like we're entering this world
that is increasingly volatile
increasingly ambiguous but at the same
time that really runs up against like
how we're individually motivated uh as
professionals where a lot of us really
want to get good at a thing and have
Mastery and it really like requires
handling this uncertainty complexity
volatility is like a personal discipline
as well as an organizational discipline
as far as like that personal resilience
handling that in certain complexity is
what is going to make the organization
resilient and that's actually quite hard
to build and it's a very rare rare skill
set
um and a lot of it's about you know well
one and I hope you like how this this
graph frame this of like how well can
you predict your actions and how much do
you know about the situation and like on
both of those axes uh it's becoming
increasingly so that you know very
little about the situation you really
can't predict your actions and like the
ability for uh
for expertise to really navigate through
that is difficult is not is much less
effective it's much more about
cross-functional
um collaboration
and Daniel blue do you want to take
anything on that
cool
okay I'm going to read this claim from
the book generative processes of
top-down bottom-up hypothesis testing
I.E prediction error minimization rather
than top-down rule-based simplification
are guiding the path to navigating a
discontinuous world I'm just going to
read these yellow parts
uh in fact
rather tame uncertainty in fact
heuristics rather team uncertainty
heuristics reinforce dominant Logics in
the form of pattern recognition and tend
to disregard dissonant bottom-up stimuli
as noise
in fact heuristics May reinforce the
phenomenon of deliberate ignorance and
tame curiosity is information enriching
drive as a foundation for prediction
error minimization I I really liked this
quote from the book and thought that it
kind of maybe sums up like the argument
against heuristics and also this
top-down bottom-up circular causality
that we've been discussing through the
chapter
Daniel
a little bit uncertain about heuristics
for information enrichment and epistemic
drive cannot be a heuristic
if so that close the loop
so that's like the reward function I
mean we've had this this discussion many
times like you know the epistemic and
pragmatic value when you knock out one
side of the equation what do you have
left and
um so yeah can your heuristic merely be
infosampling I think that that's
probably fair but yeah a subtle
technical detail probably
uh Tyler cognitive maps all right cogman
maps are closely related to heuristics
and can be considered the form of
visualizing sense making in form of
graphic representations that locate
people in relation to their information
environments uh Maps provide a frame of
reference for what is known and what is
believed
um so you know I've actually made a lot
of cognitive Maps myself on various
Consulting projects and what's kind of
funny about cognitive Maps is that
they're actually really useful to make
as like the person who is making them
like as you go through the process of
making a cognitive map you can feel like
oh like I understand the complexity of
this organization
um pretty well at this point and I can
actually like hold it all in my mind at
one time but the problem with that is
that all those two problems one is that
no one has understands your cognitive
map at all it's only useful to you and
then the other problem is that it it
basically immediately becomes outdated
and does not reflect how the
organization actually actually works uh
and so even like a month two months
later it's like completely useless even
to yourself
um yeah you know John has a good quote
of this where he really says that this
cognitive map isn't really useful for
the purposes of free energy governance
so he says cognitive mapping is
represented of the deterministic view of
the world akin to a physical cause and
effect chain and she should be
considered rather an anti-clocked in the
face of discontinuous Market
environments
um so yeah it's really not something
that you're going to be able to fully
map out
um
how governance works or how an
organization works this is actually
something that I'm thinking a lot about
over the past couple of months in the
context of dows of like can you model
the flow of value and power completely
within
um an organization as code uh and I
think what jean would say is probably
not if you can't it's not fully like
it's deterministic model of cause and
effects it's really something more of a
social process that's a little bit more
ambiguous and philosophy and hard to
nail down
um Dale blue we haven't picked out here
so like on the one hand I don't know
like cognitive Maps like when I was
taught about them in college they made
no sense to me I hated them I was like
this is the dumbest thing I've ever
heard of but then like when you get into
process flow like in writing code and in
like system design they kind of like
make sense like like an experimental
design chart so I don't know I'm back
and forth on the can you read your own
cognitive map sometimes like if you
can't I would argue that if you can't
read your own cognitive map that it's
not a good one how about that
uh okay
um claim okay it is neurosciences
predictive coding that allows us to take
management researches sense making
perspective as well as Nexus of
structure and cognition one step further
to provide a more complete and relevant
framework for applying sensing and sense
making in the context of strategic
renewal effectively sensing and sense
making are empowered by the circular
causality between top-down knowledge
structures prediction models predictions
hypotheses and guesses and bottom-up
stimuli data stemming from resource
markets I just thought it was important
to include this claim here I feel like
it sums up a lot of what is written in
this chapter
um okay so we'll talk a little bit about
abductive reasoning
um and this picture on the left shows
like inductive reasoning which is like
when you have a specific observation you
come to a general conclusion about
um that specific observation uh like if
you see you know three men wearing white
shirts in a room and then you might say
like oh all the men wear white shirts
but it might just be a coincidence right
um and then like deductive reasoning
um where you have a general rule and you
come to a specific conclusion like you
know all the men have to be wearing
white shirts in this situation and so
you conclude that the men in this room
will be wearing white shirts so that's
like a a deductive reasoning and then
you have this abductive reasoning like
where you have this incomplete
observation where you see like some of
the men in the room wearing white shirts
and you don't know anything about the
rules right and so so like you have this
incomplete observation and you make your
best prediction like um
like oh I guess some percentage of the
men here like to wear white or something
like that so this incomplete observation
coming to this best prediction I
probably did a horrible job at specific
examples but those were just like sorry
off the top of my head
um so that's like this this reasoning
logic uh and a quote from the text
abductive reasoning usually begins with
a surprising observation or experience
this is what shatters our habit and
motivates us to create a hypothesis that
might resolve the anomaly abduction is
an inferential procedure in which we
create a conjecture that if it were
would make part of would make the
surprising anomaly part of our normal
understanding of the world
um so I liked this idea of linking
abduction to surprise and I just wanted
to point out the um
the live stream number 47 about active
inference and abduction
um and we discussed more than one paper
in this live stream so just
um to read a quick quote from this
specific paper
um this paper it's uh P pietardenin I
probably butchered that and Majid Benny
and I think Majid was on that stream
with us and this paper says uh the focus
is on the allegiance between the
nomenclatures of active and abductive
inferences as the proper place to begin
reaching at The Wider Target the paper
outlines key conceptual elements
involved in a naturalistic rendering of
Pierce's late semiotic and logical
notion of abductive reasoning and
targeting a cognitive biological model
of abduction which preserves the
functional Integrity of an organism and
fulfills existential imperative for
living beings evidence of existence and
this paper was awesome like totally
mind-blowing and I can't do it justice
in like you know the five minutes or
whatever time we have here so if you
want to learn more about abduction and
the relationship to active inference I
suggest go check out this live stream or
read this paper
um unless you guys have comments here we
can move on forward yeah there's one
comment on that is it like I found it
really challenging often to like in an
organizational context to toggle between
inductive deductive and abductive
reasoning where it's like a lot of times
people get confused which kind of
reasoning you're actually using if you
do something that is kind of more
adductive like hey like here's what I'm
seeing here's my best guess like
throwing things at the wall like then
you get trapped into these things like
well how do you really know that's
that's true and you're like yeah like
that's the point like I don't like I
don't know that's true but like we're
like really just trying to like this is
a creative act we're doing together of
like trying to come up with some
hypothesis
um at just like this is a really
specialized skill set and it's like
quite hard
so yeah
and funny in the book I don't think we
pulled this code out I almost did but I
was like I'll leave it be but like Jean
I don't know if he's quoting someone
else or he just says like you know
objective reasoning is like any
hypothesis is good enough like whatever
like like so it's just kind of like you
know I don't know shooting arrows in the
dark um it kind of made it sound like
that but but there actually can be quite
a bit of Art and Science to abductive
reasoning
okay
well so John lays out a few different
Frameworks for thinking about Collective
sense making and specifically like how
you connect different levels of the
hierarchy together like since we get one
at the individual and like you know
leveling that up through organizational
sense making
um and so he talks about these like six
different models of collective sense
making and it wasn't necessarily saying
like hey I am fully behind each of one
of these but he's more just talking
about like prior work and um how to
think about like the gaps of how they
line up to free energy governance so
let's go through each one of them right
the 4i model
um so the 4i models this is
um the intuiting interpreting
integrating and institutionalizing and
so this is really thinking about how
some sticking flows through the
individual level and then bubbles up
through different levels of
socialization up into
institutionalization uh so Crossings for
I model including interpreting
integrating and institutionalizing as
applied to the context of strategic
renewal provides the framework for the
process of transmorping individual
sensing and sense making cognition to
firm level strategic action intuiting
and interpreting a hypothesis starts at
the individual level and subsequently
the interpretation says making process
becomes socialized integrated and
institutionalized at the fur level and
so this whole process is uh is goal
directed it's not just taking you know
Bottoms Up stimuli and then somehow
magically transforming it into
institutional processes it is really
goal directed and hypothesis driven of
uh really inactive and saying hey this
is what we believe about the world in
the scenes actually is actually the case
um and I think John has an interesting
point about the score I model that like
a lot of times organizations really
don't view themselves as being act
creators of their uh of their world are
really
um especially when you contact yourself
like the board gives himself as more
passive receptacles of information
um and so this whole process of sense
making from the individual level to the
organizational level is really like an
active process driven specifically
driven by the board
Lou or down she had anything to add here
um
all right tension-based view so
attention basically this is another
model that is similarly connecting both
the individual level of cognition to the
institutional level it just has like a
different spit on it and different uh
emphasis and so in this model
the idea is that you need attention to
make decisions right like you need to
put some focus and energy to make a
decision but individuals and
consequently firms have limited
attention right so like this is just
like this fundamental constraint on your
ability to make decisions is that you
just don't have the time or energy to
devote to every single position
um and so you know your individual
cognition is constrained and because
your individual cognition is constrained
uh so your social cognition and like
that social cognition is shaped by
different factors that it's like social
factors cultural factors economic
factors and that social cognition those
forces that shape like situational
contacts that shape your social social
cognition those manifest and are
institutionalized in the organizational
competition and that is like rules the
positions the players and the resources
so if you guys are familiar with like
Eleanor ostrom's model of like thinking
about
um kind of how common resource
organizations develop it's kind of like
the same exact framework that she uses
um so this is really this is very
consistent with free energy governance
though it doesn't really capture like
that inactive process of uh reality
construction it's much more about just
like thinking about attention and how
that bubbles up through different levels
of the hierarchy
uh blue Daniel anything out here
all right Dynamic capability View
so uh the aim of dynamic capabilities
research is ambitious to understand half
perms can't sustain a competitive
Advantage by responding to and creating
environmental change this is from what
from helpat who as one of the main
components of this type of
um of dynamic capability view they also
want to say that Dynamic capabilities
are
the capacity of an organization to
purposefully create extend and modify uh
it's resource based uh so this is like
very consistent with like how I learned
about
organizational design and evolution in
like a business school is much more
about like hey we have these kinds of
resources kind of like a Settlers of
katana almost like we have these
resources and these constraints in our
environment and this is like how we can
extend that resource facing grow over
time and it has a little more like a
deterministic bent to it
um and it's about like how you survive
changing environment so in that sense
it's like similar to free energy
governance uh but it's really more about
like strategic change it's not really
about like the individual cognition like
it doesn't really talk much about
individual cognition
um at all so it's like missing it's like
an interesting like theoretical
framework but it's not really uh
as embodied as free interview governance
and as like
um it's missing that relationship to the
individual
here
all right okay ours
um so okrs our objectives and key
results so like the idea here is that
you have a main so at every single level
of the hierarchy so let's say that your
company top of the higher piece like I
should just use this example on the
slide you want to you're the head of the
brand you want to get a thousand new
signups right that is your um
your objective
or you know your objective is increasing
brain activations and the key result
like the quantitative way you measure
that is get a thousand new signups right
so that's at the top level of the
organization and then in each level of
the hierarchy below that you have like
the sub components that would need to be
true for to get a thousand new signups
right so the things that would need to
be true to get a thousand new signups
are that uh well when you have to on the
head of content you have to get your
click-through rate above some threshold
Implement 10 12 new mediums post old or
new content on the partnership side you
have to get 10 000 event registrants uh
by Sunday right I'm sorry
um so it's basically a way of thinking
about like how goals Cascade from the
top level of the organization and filter
down through the other levels Jesus
Christ
sorry about that
very persistent
um and so this is actually really
popular in a like especially like Tech
world uh this is pioneered by like John
door Larry Page wrote this book
um about measure called measure what
matters it's about like a quantitative
way of thinking about organizational
design and goal setting
and so I've actually done this a lot at
different organizations and it can be
powerful and I think the genre really
likes it he says okay ours had proven to
be an invaluable Dynamic tool to Foster
informal exchanges at the field level of
resource markets approximating
self-organization because each level of
the hierarchy is has the responsibility
for themselves to set their own okr that
aligns with the next level of the
hierarchy right so it can be like really
Dynamic that and uh have that self-organ
organizing quality however a problem
with it and this is not something that
Jean brought up is something from my own
experience is that like
especially in a startup context things
are moving so quickly that okr is very
very often become outdated pretty much
like immediately and so you'll set an
okr for a quarter and then you're a
month down the line and so much has
changed like the context is so different
that like like this okr obviously
doesn't matter anymore
um and that's a huge problem and so like
you need some way of like changing your
cares dynamically but the problem is is
that okrs take a lot of work to set up
and to socialize and to measure and so
then you like you really don't have the
resources necessarily to do that and
that is a huge challenge uh there's also
like huge issues with doing okrs and
that it's like some uh some version of
like good Arts law where like when you
measure when your measure becomes a
Target it ceases to be a good measure
whereas like these different levels of
the organization can over optimize for
some like arbitrary metric that they
need to get a promotion which sometimes
that can be aligned with the
organization but like in quickly
changing environments it can become
quickly not aligned with the
organization actually needs so there's
like a lot of pushback for okrs right
now it's unclear but like I think
they're there's probably some
formulation of ocaras that's more
Dynamic and more responsive to bottom-up
stimuli
um but they
they can be really hard to
operationalize
but theoretically amazing way of
connecting different levels of the organ
of Jesus Christ all right different
levels of the organization
um all right excuse the next one
collaborative intelligence
all right so the drive for
self-organizing mechanisms gradually
move from employee empowerment and
collective intelligence and form of
crowdsourcing deploying the journey the
power of information Technologies to tap
into the collective knowledge base to co
to collaborative intelligence CQ
emphasizing the need for a shift in the
leadership model from having all the
answers to raising the right questions
as digital tools are increasingly
deployed to enable goal direct and
intelligence deliberations and
distributed multi-intelligence systems
uh and so like to to think about like
what this actually means like in
practice oftentimes it's not the case
where it's like you have some like
really huge robust system where every
person in the organization is like
seamlessly sharing like their insights
and their data like that's not really
how it works it much more works that
it's like uh you have specialized sense
makers within the organization and uh
consistent ways of processing data and
sharing that data so for example you'll
have like an IT team they create
um
they have like a central data warehouse
where they
put all the data together they clean it
and sanitize it in a consistent way and
then you have embedded kind of sense
makers like kind of Consultants or
analysts at different levels of the
organization processing that data
sharing insights with each other
socializing across the organization and
that tends to be kind of like how it's
generally structured especially in like
a laptop companies
all right an open strategy would be is
kind of an extension of that it's like
the extreme extension of collaborative
intelligence
um so open strategy is categorically
different traditional top level
strategizing and Quant and qualitatively
different from bottom line strategizing
so open strategy is unique and it's
overall transparency wide inclusiveness
and Central use of social I.T to
effectively enable mass participation in
summary uh open strategies Brad is
rather project Centric rather than
coherent new strategy governance
framework the very limitations
transpiring through the various case
studies suggests that open strategy is
likely to battle with schwarmer's uh
three enemies or inner voices of
resistance uh the voice of judgment the
voice of cynicism and the voice of fear
so like open strategy is this kind of
idea where it's like hey this strategy
can emerge through this kind of like
Bottoms Up information processing we all
have the information available to us
wouldn't be purely on this top-down
decision maker for like synthesizing all
of this but rather we could all do that
together in something more robust will
emerge through that process and this is
like a specialty a popular it's been
like one like two organizations or
holocracy that that kind of decision
making is like the gold standard for how
it could happen
um though like you brought some
interesting use cases about uh things
like IBM I think it's Pepsi a few other
different use cases where their
experience with this is mixed and when
he says this is a project Center Centric
rather than a coherent new strategy
governance framework like it's easy to
do this more in a project setting
because you can think about what the
relevant pieces of information are and
who all the stakeholders are that you
want to involve but to do that
dynamically means that you're like
continuously bringing in new information
changing a new stakeholder responding to
decision making processes between those
stakeholders that's super hard to do
like on a continuous basis rather than
like a limited scope project basis so
it's like a kind of unclear
how to make up a strategy work over like
a long and definite period of time
um
yeah blue dialing thing to add here
yeah I mean just like one one last Point
here is that like I really like I
brought the voice of the inner voices of
resistance the voice of judgment the
voice of cynicism and the voice of fear
and that's like really been kind of a
this feeling I've had as I've been
reading this book of like yes like this
wave integrating top-down and Bottoms Up
stimuli together like sounds great and
it's like totally the right way
to do it but sometimes the reality of
being an organization is that you're
dealing with people's like personal fear
and that really holds you back from
being able to um
to like dynamically change like people
want stability people want Mastery
um people want things to be the word the
way that they were the same in the past
and like that's like a very deeply I
think human thing I'm not sure if that's
a thing that's you know unique about
modern organizations uh and like you're
really going up against that when you're
trying to develop these more like
Dynamic systems of thinking about
purpose and meaning and sense making and
to me in my mind that feels like the
central challenge of free energy
governance I'm not sure John would agree
with that but that to me that feels like
the huge role you have to overcome
foreign
so moving into the second section which
is um but much smaller so we'll try to
be fast uh okay there's a claim here
strategic renewal is an iterative
process of belief action and learning
where periods of incremental adjustment
single Loop learning are broken by
bursts of revolutionary change double
Loop learning it is only when we start
expressing beliefs as probability
distributions and action as a state that
precedes perception conditioned by a
markovian boundary intermediating the
internal and external States all
dedicated all dedicated in circular
causality to continuously optimizing the
updating of beliefs I.E learning and
mathematically self-consistent model
emerges
um so strategic renewal uh is he is
using is using a definition put forward
in this article uh by Schmidt in 2018
this book adopts a cross-hierarchical
capabilities driven and action
action-centric learning perspective in
defining strategic renewal which is best
captured by Schmidt strategic renewal
involves a transformation of the firm's
core capabilities associated with
competitive Advantage concerns the
entire organization and has implications
across organizational levels and is
essential to break past dependence and
ensure the firm's long-term survival
um and another claim he makes here is to
approach strategic renewal as an upper
echelon Centric top-down only challenge
is nonsense given the importance of
social interactions to knowledge
development and organizational learning
we believe that renewal can be
understood best as a system of
relational or social exchanges which is
effectively the essence of reality
construction indeed once strategic
renewal is embraced as a system of
relational or social exchanges the need
for across hierarchical connect emerges
and I just wanted to bring up this
figure this is like the action
perception loop from thinking through
other Minds a variational approach to
cognition and culture we've had this on
the live stream before I can't remember
and didn't look up which live stream
number it was
um but but in this paper they really
illustrate how
this relational and social exchanges is
like interaction with the niche
environment helps us come to a mutual
consensus in a social kind of way and so
if you would like more information there
I recommend this paper
okay and then Bijan talks about top down
versus bottom up strategic renewal
the more dominant a top-down directed
induced rather than bottom-up inspired
autonomous strategic renewal process the
more likely that critical intelligence
form resource markets maybe that should
be from resource markets is ignored and
transient and transformation-bearing
Market signals are lost
in the absence of a circular top-down
bottom-up organizational learning The
Firm may become trapped in top
leadership's dominant Logics highly
dependent on m a joint venture driven
Innovation and increasingly disconnected
from the very intelligence the firm's
field close to Resource markets beholds
eventually Financial control M A and
alliancing is likely to squeeze out
strategic control in-house Innovation
making the firm potentially rather more
than less vulnerable to survival risk as
Innovation can no longer can be
generated from within the firm did you
guys have any comments here top down
versus bottom up
okay
um and financial versus strategic
control Tyler do you want to read this
one for me
sure Financial strategic control
respectively for like curvilinearly to
confirm performance too low too much of
one or the others potentially entropy
bound the firm is challenged to find an
optimal balance between external and
internal Innovation to power continuous
strategic renewal as a sustainable
foundation for performance and survival
indeed the question arises how did this
Balance Financial and strategic control
and whether the board of directors
potentially assumes critical and unique
strategic role in the process
so yeah I mean I think just something to
add here to you is
um like a lot of times these frames
build or buy and the the startup the
traditional Stark wisdom of like how you
might balance these two decisions of
like build versus buy as that like build
is we call that strategic right like
these are the things that are like the
core and Central to your purpose this is
like the core like engine of how you
create value in the world
um and by are the things where and by
can mean a couple different things it
doesn't actually mean necessarily it can
mean more like Partnerships and plugging
into the external ecosystem and so
that'd be like using someone else's API
for something that is not necessarily
essential to you like stripe Payment
Processing right and so it's this way
that you can like both have a
sustainable competitive advantage while
at the same time
um kind of
not using your resources and your energy
and your attention for something that's
like not core to who you are
cool thank you
um okay I think this is our final claim
from the book
strategic renewal research is in need of
a more comprehensive framework
structurally resolving the hierarchical
top-down bottom-up learning disconnect
cognitively embracing environment as a
matter of enactment and in terms of
capabilities balancing financial and
strategic control as well as
exploitation and exploration the board
of directors should be integrated as a
distinct cognitive variable into the
community of interactions but more
importantly the question arises whether
the board possesses the right
capabilities to be of strategic
relevance in discontinuous Market
environments
um I think that that's all so if you
guys have any comments
um if not we can move into some
concluding thoughts
sure
well
the book is subtitled reframing the
strategy governance conversation
so I think we're getting chapter by
chapter a clear review of the
positioning and the contribution of free
energy governance and towards the middle
of the book things get really
detailed with respect to the
applications of the active inference
framework so far we've seen more of a
introductory opening Salvo and a call
for Need for integration above and
beyond the current existing practices
which I think Tyler did a great job um
conveying like some of the real world's
strengths and weaknesses and challenges
of of all these different strategies
yes to add to that like I'm really
excited for
um how we move this into an applied
setting because kind of like
you're combining the fox and the
Hedgehog model like this is something
I've actually thought about a lot to
little success and it's a huge problem
especially thinking about things like
okrs have probably they become updated
like how do you create a model of the
world while simultaneously communicating
like hey this model is subject to change
like this is a work in progress that
we're co-creating together
um and like kind of going against
people's individual resistance of not
wanting change and wanting things to be
stable like I don't have a clue of how
you actually really do that I'm curious
I really hope Sean has a good answer for
that
awesome well we'll see you guys next
week uh for chapter three uh peace and
enjoy your rest of your day or night
wherever you might be and your temporal
existence